Guide to the Donald Clifford Gallup Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- April 2001 Acquisition, 1754-1979; 15; 1.46; (2 boxes)
  Organized under three headings: Writings, Printed Material, and Correspondence.
  - Writings
    - Thornton Wilder Journals (1939-1969), undated; 12 (Box 116)
    - Lee, Lawrence: "Tomorrow Good-Bye", undated
    - Warren, Robert Penn. "William Faulkner and His South", 1951 March 13
  - Printed Material
    - A Catalogue of the Published and Unpublished Writings of Gertrude Stein, 1941
    - The Grenfell Press, prospectus, undated
    - J. Howard Woolner catalogue 57, 1979
    - "Murder in the Cathedral", theater program signed by T.S. Eliot, undated
  - Correspondence
    - Barnes, Djuna: 3 typed letters, signed, to Peter Whigham, 1953
    - Barney, Natalie: 16 autograph letters, signed, and 2 calling cards to Richard Aldington, 1927-1928
    - Baretti, Joseph
      - Autograph letter, signed, to Don Rimigio, in Italian, 1754 May 30
      - Autograph letter, signed, to [Sir Robert Chambers and his wife], 1786 April 30
    - Bosschere, Jean de: Autograph letter, signed, to John Cournos, 1921 August 19
    - Brown, Ford Maddox: Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Matthews, [18]89 January 11
    - Dibdin, T. F.: Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Sir", [18]40 October 9
    - Eliot, T. S.: Honorary degrees from Harvard and Oxford, printed material and one photograph., 1947-1948
    - Cabell, James Branch: 9 typed letters, signed, to Donald C. Gallup with his carbon replies, 1948-1950
    - Eastlake, Charles L.: Autograph letter, signed, to E. M. Ward, 1853 August 11
    - Epstein, Trevor: Autograph letter, signed, to unidentified, 1954 November 20
    - Fletcher, Constance: Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Miles; Fletcher, J. C.: 2 autograph letters signed to Rev. S. J. Spaulding; clipping, 1885-1887, 1938
    - Hartley, Marsden: to Mrs. and Mrs. H. W. Eliot, with two photographs, undated
    - Hunt, W. Holman: Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Mangles, [no year] April 19
    - Jepson, Edgar
      - Autograph letter, signed, to [A. R.] Orage, 1907 July 5
      - Postcard to New Age Press, 1907 May 4
      - Autograph letter, signed, to Holbrook Jackson, 1914 March 28
      - "Occasional Reflections," manuscript, signed, undated
      - "Occasional Reflections," manuscript, signed, undated
    - Jones, David: Autograph letter, signed, to Christopher Sandford, 1951 October 26
    - La Farge, John: 9 autograph letters, signed, to "Miss Young", 1908-1910, undated
    - Landseer, Tho[mas]: Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear", [no year] May 24
    - Wyndham, Lewis
      - Autograph letter, signed, to Middleton [?], 1927 February 27
      - 2 typed letters, signed, to Mrs. Lynd, 1934
      - 4 autograph letters, signed, to John Gawsworth, 1932
    - Lindsay, Vachel: 4 autograph letters, signed, to Christopher Morley, 1921-1922 (Box 117)
    - Lizars, W. H.: Autograph letter, signed, to W. T. MacDonald, undated
    - Lowell, Robert: Typed letter, signed, to Mrs. Henry W. Eliot, 1956 November 16
    - Millais, John: Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Sir", 1896 January 21
    - Moore, Marianne: 4 typed letters, signed, and 1 autograph letter, signed, to Donald C. Gallup, with his carbon replies, 1952-1965
    - Palmer, Samuel: Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. [Utterton?], 1870 August 19
    - Plarr, Victor: "An Alsatian Episode:" manuscript, corrected, signed, undated
    - Prout, Samuel: 18 autograph letters, signed, to John Clowes Grundy and R. H. Grundy; Third Person autograph letter to Henry Webb with a receipt from ["Grundy"]; Autograph letter, signed, to "Grundy" from J. P. [Gellespere?]., 1832-1851
    - Rathbone, Basil: Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Jewett, 1926 April 22
    - Rodker, John: Autograph letter, signed, to Clement Shorter, [no year] April 4
    - Sargent, John Singer: Autograph letter, signed, to [?], [no year] April 8
    - Sinclair, May: 7 autograph letters, signed, to J. R. Tutin, 1894-1897
    - Thomson, Virgil
      - Autograph letter, signed, to Lindley Williams Hubbell, 1929 March 4
      - Typed letter, signed, to David James, 1950 April 19
      - Autograph letter, signed, to Donald C. Gallup, 1963 January 10
    - Ward, John: Autograph letter, signed, to James Ward, 1817 May 10
    - Wise, Tho[ma]s J.: Autograph letter, signed, to "Lamperley", 1923 December 31
- June 2001 Acquisition, 1947; 16; 0.21; (1 box)
  The 2001 Acquisition consists of a printed edition of A Bibliographic Check-list of the Writings of T. S. Eliot with manuscript notes.
  - Gallup, Donald C. A Bibliographical Check-List of the Writings of T. S. Eliot, 1947 (Box 118)
- September 2001 Acquisition, 1942; 17; 0.21; (1 box)
  The September 2001 Acquisition consists of typescripts and handwritten drafts of two writings by Donald Gallup.
  - Untitled lecture on T. S. Eliot, undated (Box 119)
  - "Walt Whitman and Modern Poetry", 1942, undated; 2
- May 2008 Acquisition, 1907-2000; 18; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The May 2008 Acquisition consists chiefly of correspondence, newspaper clippings and other printed material, as well as a photograph of Donald Gallup.
  - The New Journal, Vol. 15, Number 2, 1982 October 15 (Box 120)
  - "A Song of the Virgin Mother", undated
  - "Università Commerciale Luigi Bocconi", undated
  - Lewis, Sinclair, circa 1907-1940; 2
    Includes newspapers, clippings, and other printed ephemera.
  - Polytechnic (1908), undated
  - Newspaper clippings, letters, and other printed ephemera removed from books, circa 1949-1981; 22
  - Le Propre des Seints, undated (Box 121)
  - Henderson, Archie. Ezra Pound: A Bibliographical Supplement, 1986
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1994-2000; 4
  - Photograph of Donald Gallup, undated
  - "O'Neill on World Stages", 1994
- May 2008 Acquisition, 1924-1933, undated; 19; 0.38; (3 boxes)
  The May 2008 Acquisition consists of artwork by Theresa Garrett Eliot, Edward McKnight Kauffer, and John Storrs, and photographs by George Platt Lynes.
  - Artwork
    - T. S. Eliot, crayon drawing done from a photograph, 1933; Eliot, Theresa Garrett, 1884-1981 (Box 122 (Oversize))
    - Drawing for Eliot's "Doris's Dream Songs" as printed in The Chapbook, A Miscellany (1924), circa 1924; Kauffer, E. McKnight (Edward McKnight), 1890-1954 (Box 122 (Oversize))
    - Drawing for Robinson Crusoe (1929), circa 1929; Kauffer, E. McKnight (Edward McKnight), 1890-1954 (Box 122 (Oversize))
    - Sketch for a poster, undated; Kauffer, E. McKnight (Edward McKnight), 1890-1954 (Box 122 (Oversize))
    - ["Thornton"], abstract pencil drawing, undated; Storrs, John Henry Bradley, 1885-1956 (Box 123)
  - Photographs
    - Black and white photograph of T. S. Eliot, undated; Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955 (Box 124)
    - Black and white photograph of Marianne Moore, undated; Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955 (Box 124)
- February 1983 Acquisition, 1979; 20; 0.42 linear feet (1 box)
  The February 1983 Acquisition consists of photocopies of annotated and corrected typescript drafts and of corrected page proofs of Thornton Wilder's American Characteristics and Other Essays (1979). The photocopied material includes copied and original annotations. The essays include the inaugural Charles Eliot Norton lecture at Harvard University, and two subsequent Norton lectures, as well as essays which include Wilder's analyses of the works of James Joyce, Gertrude Stein, Johann Goethe, George Bernard Shaw, and others. Copies of Wilder's introductions to various Gertrude Stein works are also included. Gallup saved typescripts of these works which include revisions, corrections, and notes. Also included are Gallup's typed correspondence with Susan Arterian and Frances Lindley at Harper and Row.
  Arranged in the order in which it was recieved by the library.
  - American Characteristics and Other Essays typescript photocopies
    Organized by page number and in the order it was recieved by the library.
    American Characteristics and Other Essays is a collection of works published in 1979. It includes "Toward an American Language", a Charles Eliot Norton lecture given at Harvard in 1950. That lecture was edited and published in the Atlantic in 1952. The remaining essays included in this collection were written at different points in Wilder's career. Donald Gallup was instrumental in getting the essay collection published. This series contains typescript photocopies of the collection with correspondence about the book and some annotations.
    - American Characteristics and Other Essays" title page, table of contents, and "Toward an American Language" typescript copy, 1979; undated (Box 128)
      Also includes correspondence between Donald Gallup and Frances Lindley.
    - "Toward an American Language" (2 folders), undated (Box 128)
    - "The American Loneliness", undated (Box 128)
      Includes "The American Loneliness", the second Charles Eliot Norton lecture.
    - "Emily Dickinson" and "Culture in Democracy", undated (Box 128)
      "Emily Dickinson" is the the third Charles Eliot Norton lecture delivered by Wilder. "Culture in Democracy" was written in English and delivered by Wilder in German when he recived the German Publishers and Booksellers Peace Prize.
    - "Goethe and World Literature" and "James Joyce", undated (Box 128)
      "Goethe and World Literature" was a lecture given by Wilder at the Goethe Convention in Aspen, Colorado in 1949. "James Joyce" was written and pbulished in Poetry, A Magazine of Verse in 1944.
    - "Giordano Bruno's Last Meal in Finnegan's Wake ", undated (Box 128)
      "Giordino Bruno's Last Meal in Finnegan's Wake " was published in the Hudson Review in 1963.
    - "Gertrude Stein's The Geographical History of America ", undated (Box 128)
      "Gertrude Stein's The Geographical History of America " is an introduction to a book of the same name, published in 1936.
    - "On Reading the Great letter Writers", undated (Box 128)
      Wilder most likely delivered this lecture at Yale in the 1930s.
    - "Sophocles' Oedipus the King " introduction, "George Bernard Shaw", and The Angel that Troubled the Waters preface, undated (Box 128)
      Sophocles' Oedipus the King " is an introduction written for an edition of the play published in 1955. "George Bernard Shaw" was not previously published. The foreword to The Angel that Troubled the Waters and other Plays was published in 1928.
    - "A Preface for Our Town ", preface to Three Plays: Our Town, The Skin of Our Teeth, The Matchmaker, "Noting the Nature of Farce", and "Some Thoughts on Playwriting", undated (Box 128)
      "A Preface for Our Town " was written but not published in 1938. The preface to Three Plays: Our Town, The Skin of Our Teeth, The Matchmaker was published in 1957. "Noting the Nature of Farce" was published in 1939. "Some Thoughts on Playwrighting" was published in 1941.
    - Richard Beer-Hofmann's Jaakobs Traum, "Frederick J.E. Woodbridge", "Christian Berard", and "John Marin", undated (Box 128)
      Richard Beer-Hofmann's Jaackobs Traum " was published in 1946. "Frederick J. E. Woodbridge" was included in the Commemorative Tributes of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1905-1941 published in 1941. "John Marin" was part of the Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Letters and the National Institute of Arts and Letters.
    - "Thomas Mann", "Chauncey Brewster Tinker", and the introduction to "Sir Philip Sassoon's The Third Route ", undated (Box 128)
      "Thomas Mann" and "Chauncey Brewster Tinker" were published in the Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Letters and the National Institute of Arts and Letters in 1957 and 1964. The introduction to The Third Route was published in 1929.
    - "New Aids Toward Dating the Early Plays of Lope de Vega", undated (Box 128)
      This paper was contributed to Varia Variorum: Festgabe dur Karl Reinhardt.
  - American Characteristics and Other Essays page proof photocopies
    Includes page proof photocopies with some annotations of American Characteristics and Other Essays.
    - Table of contents, foreword, "Toward an American Language", "The American Loneliness", "Emily Dickinson", "Culture in Democracy", and "Sophocles' Oedipus Rex", undated (Box 128)
    - Miscellaneous pages from articles on Gertrude Stein, Frederick J.E. Woodbridge, Sir Philip Sassoon, and Sophocles, circa 1979 (Box 128)
      Also includes correspondence about "American Characteristics and Other Essays".
    - "American Loneliness", undated (Box 128)
    - "American Loneliness", "Emily Dickinson", "Culture in Democracy", and "Sophocles' Oedipus Rex", undated (Box 128)
    - "George Bernard Shaw", "Noting the Nature of Farce", the prefaces for "Three Plays" and "Our Town", undated (Box 128)
    - "Some Thoughts on Play-Writing" and Richard Beer-Hofmann's "Jacob's Dream", undated (Box 128)
    - "Goethe and World Literature" and "On Reading the Great Letter Writers", undated (Box 128)
    - "James Joyce", "James Joyce and the Modern Novel", introduction to "Narration" and "The Geographical History of America" by Gertrude Stein, undated (Box 128)
    - Introduction to "Four in America" by Gertrude Stein, undated (Box 128)
    - "Frederick J. E. Woodbridge", "Christian Berard", "John Marin", "Thomas Mann", and "Chauncey Brewster Tinker", undated (Box 128)
    - Introduction to Sir Philip Sassoon's "The Third Route", "New Aids toward Dating the Early Plays of Lope de Vega", "Lope Pinedo", "Some Child-Actors and a Lion", "Giordano Burno's Last Meal in Finnegan's Wake", undated (Box 128)